Okay, let's see what we got here.
Seen it. Seen it.
What's this about?
At the dawn... dawn... dawn...
dawn... dawn... dawn...
Here we go.
At the dawn of time, there was
our gracious and powerful creator,
Primus.
To protect our universe,
he sacrificed his life force,
transforming himself into our planet,
Cybertron.
From within Cybertron's core,
Primus birthed the first Transformers
known as the Primes,
the most powerful Transformers, appointed
to lead and protect future generations.
To assist them,
Primus created an entity of great power,
the Matrix of Leadership.
The Matrix, there it is. Okay. Good.
Come on. Keep going.
With the Matrix in the Primes' possession,
Cybertron's natural power source, Energon,
flowed in abundance,
sustaining life across the planet.
Attention! Unauthorized movement
detected in archival vault. Sector J-3.
KDQ-12 to KDK-1.
Breaching archives in ten seconds.
For generations,
there was peace and prosperity
until the Matrix of Leadership was lost,
causing Energon to no longer flow.
Why does every legend about the Matrix
end right there?
One of these has to say what happened.
Halt, criminal! Prepare to be detained!
-Halt, criminal! Prepare to be detained!
-Hey there.
Uh-oh.
-Freeze!
-Get down!
Well, hello, guys.
Yeah, I'm so glad you're here.
Which way is the exit?
I must've taken a wrong turn.
It's that defective mining bot, Oreon Pix!
-Orion Pax.
-Who cares?
We told you to never come back here!
-Why are we all yelling?
-I'm gonna smash you!
Hold on. Hold on. No need for violence.
How about this: I run away, you chase me.
We play that game, huh?
Come on.
You're bigger, faster. It'll be fun.
He doesn't have a cog.
Let's give him a head start.
Why not? It's not like he can transform.
Oh, yeah?
Well, watch this.
Get him!
Something that flies.
Prepare to be detained! Halt, criminal!
Prepare to be detained!
Halt, criminal!
Come on! Start! Come on!
No, no, no, no!
There he is!
So long, suck--
Energon.
Evening, everyone. Pardon me.
-It's Orion.
-Seriously, again?
Okay.
Hey, fellas! Thanks for the head start.
Want to give me another one?
-You're dead!
-I'll take that as a no.
Hey! Watch where you're going!
What did you say, no-cog?
Sorry, sir, I didn't mean you.
I was referring to the bot
who was behind you.
-Where'd he go?
-The filthy red and blue bot?
Has a big mouth, squeaky joints,
gives off a corroded metallic stench?
-Where is he?
-He went that way.
When I get my hands on that bot...
All right, all clear.
Listen, D-16, I may be a little rusty,
but "corroded"? That is too far.
Let me guess. Chased out of the archives?
Yeah. I had to jump out of a window
this time. Almost died. It was wild.
And digging through ancient data
is worth dying for?
Yes, it is.
I need a new best friend.
If there are clues in our recorded history
that can help locate
the Matrix of Leadership,
they're in the archives.
Sentinel Prime, the Sentinel Prime,
is up on the surface right now
risking his life for us
in search of the Matrix.
That's exactly what I'm doing.
I'm trying to help him.
Yeah, okay.
The sooner Energon flows again,
the sooner we won't have to mine for it.
Don't you want to choose your own path,
do whatever you want?
We're miners. We mine, that's all.
No, there has got to be
something more I can do.
-I can feel it.
-Oh, yeah?
Like the time that you had a "feeling"
you could transform without a cog?
You said you were never gonna
mention that again.
It took me three days to pry you open.
Your feelings get you in trouble.
Yeah, yeah.
-Just trust in Sentinel Prime.
-I do trust in him.
Hey, if we did have cogs--
I'd transform into a shovel and beat you.
I don't like how fast you answered that.
But listen. If you did beat me,
I couldn't give you this awesome
Megatronus Prime thing I have here.
-It's cool. I'll give it to someone else.
-What Megatronus Prime thing?
It's nothing. Just a, you know,
mint-condition Megatronus Prime decal,
first edition.
What?
If you don't want it,
I can just throw it away.
Throw it away?
That's not funny. Let me see.
Wait. Don't grab. You're gonna crease it.
You know, Sentinel says
Megatronus was the--
The strongest Prime to ever live.
I know, buddy.
-Looks good on you.
-It's really cool.
-Thanks.
-Always got your back.
No matter what.
Approaching sublevel station.
Stand clear of doors.
Mining teams, prepare to unload.
Metal to the pedal, drill bits.
This is it.
How much Energon have you mined
under my leadership?
So much, Elita-1!
And how perfect is my mining record?
So perfect, Elita-1!
We are a mere 30 units of Energon away
from my promotion to supervisor.
Are you happy for me?
So happy, Elita-1!
Elita... I mean Captain... you are looking
especially shiny this morning. New polish?
Orion Pax, I'm sorry that I somehow gave
you the impression that we're friends.
Apology accepted.
Light up that wall! Let's go! Ten seconds!
Happy to take the lead today, Captain.
Feeling like I have enough power in me
to drill down and touch Primus myself.
You don't have the touch or the power.
Ready positions, rust buckets! Let's go!
She's in a good mood today.
-You ready?
-Always ready.
Let's punch in.
Here we go. This one won't be open long.
Brace it up!
Here we go! Bridge!
Brace up!
Lower channel is open.
Drill power on max!
Low bridge!
Drill it out!
I tapped a vein!
It's unstable!
We got to go. We got to move!
Evacuate!
Everyone out! Evacuate immediately!
The tunnel is closing.
I repeat, the tunnel is closing!
-You with me, D?
-On your six! Keep going!
Look out!
Jazz is stuck!
Elita, we've got a trapped miner.
I'm falling back to assist.
Negative. Do not break protocol. Evacuate!
We're gonna need more lift.
It's closing! Just grab your pack and go.
Yeah, good idea.
What? No, I didn't mean it!
Pull him clear!
Pax, what's happening?
Nothing much. Just normal
protocol-following stuff. It's all good.
That's not good.
Orion Pax, could you please exit
the tunnel of death?
Elita, it's about to get messy out there!
Go, go, go!
Run! Run!
-Hurry!
-We're not gonna make it!
Come on! Go, go, go!
What the hell, Pax?
I told you to evacuate.
-I did, eventually.
-If I get fired because of you--
Oh, please. They're not gonna fire you.
Elita-1, you're fired.
What? Why?
I followed protocol to the letter.
That is true.
I was the one who broke the rules.
No one asked you!
Darkwing, please,
I've worked too hard for this.
You are no-cog bots with limited options.
Report to waste management immediately.
Waste management?
Elita...
Next time, why don't you stop and think
before you ruin someone's life?
I'm sorry!
-Hey, Darkwing!
-Don't do it.
I may not have a cog, but my finger
can transform. Guess which one?
I'll give you a "limited option."
Excuse me, sir. Allow me.
I apologize on his behalf for the--
Why?
That really hurt.
What'd you expect? He's metal.
You know you were out of line,
talking back to a superior like that.
Darkwing was out of line. He deserves it.
Aren't you tired of being treated
like we're nothing?
He had every right to hit me.
I interfered.
Hey, and I appreciate you having my back.
I'm glad you were there with me
to get punched in the face. That was fun.
Anytime, buddy.
Attention, all sectors.
Stand by for a live transmission
from Sentinel Prime.
-He's back? He's back already?
-Maybe he found the Matrix.
Is it on? Okay, thank you.
Hello, my friends.
Hello, Iacon City!
Hello to our saviors,
the industrious miners who toil selflessly
to maintain our Energon reserves.
I celebrate you.
Humility and presence! That's leadership!
Nobody does it better!
Once again, I have narrowly returned
with my fleet
after another treacherous expedition
across the desolate, dangerous surface
of our planet.
I departed with hopes of finding
the Matrix of Leadership,
the key to bringing balance to Cybertron.
I regret to inform you
that we've returned empty-handed.
This is a setback, but not a failure.
Rest assured,
I will find the Matrix of Leadership
so that Energon can flow again.
But that's in the future.
Right now,
I think we all deserve a little fun!
Tomorrow, there will be no work.
All shifts off
because tomorrow is the Iacon 5000!
-Yeah!
-Yes!
My favorite event.
A high-octane race all across Iacon City.
Let's all see which competitor can prove
they are truly more than meets the eye.
D.
Hey, D.
Oh, good, you're up.
Come on. I have an idea.
Whatever this is, it better be good.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Listen.
All right, what if... what if...
what if tomorrow
we ran in the Iacon 5000, huh?
What if I kill you for waking me up?
No, no, hear me out.
-We don't even have to win!
-That's good, because we wouldn't.
But if we beat just one Transformer,
it proves we're just as good as they are.
Not only would we go down in history,
the mining bots that did the impossible,
but we would show everyone
that we're capable of so much more.
Or we get publicly humiliated
and then busted back to tier one.
Yeah, but at least
we would've done something, you know?
-Pax...
-Come on, D.
Pax.
We're mining bots who can't transform.
We can't fly, we can't roll,
we can't race.
Come on. Let's go.
All right, fine.
Yeah, maybe you're right.
Maybe.
The Iacon 5000 is finally here!
I have a surprise for you. Come on.
Where are you going?
The stadium's that way.
-Yeah, I know. Follow me.
-Great. We're gonna be late now.
I wanted good seats.
We came all this way to miss
the opening ceremony. This is wonderful!
Trust me, I know what I'm doing.
Hold up!
Get caught in one of those,
it'll launch you halfway across the city.
Okay, where are you taking me?
Don't be a glitch,
this will be totally worth it. Trust me.
Hey, you don't be a glitch.
Look, I know this is fun for you,
like, we're joking around,
but if you make me miss
any part of the Iacon 5000,
I swear I will smelt your face
right off your...
Welcome to the Iacon 5000. There they are.
Put your hands together as today's
competitors are taking the field.
Look! There's Thunderglide and Behemoth!
This is unbelievable!
I feel like I'm in the race!
You did this for me?
No.
I did this for us.
And now the moment
you've all been waiting for.
The icon of Iacon!
The savior of Cybertron!
Quintessons fear him, but we love him!
Our leader, the one and only...
Sentinel Prime!
I love you, Sentinel!
Yes! It feels so good
to be here with you all today.
My friends. My Cybertronian family.
It has been precisely 50 cycles
since the Quintessons attacked our home.
Fifty cycles since we lost
the Matrix of Leadership
and our Energon supply dried up.
Fifty cycles since the battle
that killed the other Primes,
my brothers and sisters in arms.
Today we honor the Primes
who gave their lives for ours,
and we show them that the strength
of Cybertron will never be diminished.
Racers, on your marks!
I can't believe we get to watch
from the starting line,
the best seats in the house!
Why'd you bring jetpacks?
Get set!
It's time to show them
we are more than meets the eye.
Oh, no.
And they're off!
-Are you crazy?
-Sure feels like it.
The Iacon 5000 has begun!
I'm sorry, are those miners in the race?
Miners! Those are miners, like us!
I can't believe what I'm seeing here!
Miners trying to run in the Iacon 5000!
You've got to be kidding me.
This is insane!
There are miners in the race!
-No way!
-They can't even transform!
It's Orion Pax and D-16!
This is a first in Iacon 5000 history.
How are they going to survive?
If we survive this, I'm gonna kill you!
I accept those terms.
It's Tailwind pulling into the lead
down the main stretch
followed by Strafe and Skyfire!
Hey, look out!
-I owe you one.
-More like a thousand.
I can't believe we're not in last place!
Eat it, miner!
-Darkwing delivers a devastating blow.
-Got you.
-We're not fast enough!
-Improvise!
-Hey, get off!
-Spinout! Big fan!
Jetstorm, I'm so sorry. Big fan!
Get off!
Time it just right!
And... now!
Move!
And the miners have fallen way behind.
We can now focus
on the real contenders in this race.
I don't believe it!
The miners take down Darkwing!
Miners!
Great effort, Darkwing!
That worked! It actually worked!
Is this the dumbest thing we've ever done?
Oh, yeah, it's up there!
Wait!
Go, go, go!
A four-bot pileup in the magnetic tunnel,
and the two miners are now
in first position!
This is unbelievable!
D!
No. Go. Leave me!
No, we do this together.
One miner is now carrying the other
mere steps from the finish line
in the most amazing, sensational,
dramatic, heartrending, exciting,
thrilling finish in the history of--
We have a winner!
Chromia comes from behind
to take the prize.
Talk about an Iacon 5000 for the ages.
Well, second place is still pretty good.
Paging Dr. Ratchet.
Dr. Ratchet to Medical Bay 94.
Do not worry.
You will be fixed up in no time.
Did I win?
You participated.
Yay!
So...
how long do you think we'll be here?
I'm not talking to you.
You know what? I can't believe
you made me do that. We are so screwed!
Thought you weren't talking to me.
Hey, look, I know it's all
a big joke to you. But not me.
I was paying my dues. I was going places.
And now they're gonna bust me down
I don't even know how many tiers!
I'm sorry, D.
But come on. Didn't you feel it?
Even for just a second,
didn't you feel liberated?
Didn't you feel like
you were something else?
Like you could be more
than what they say you are?
Yeah, I felt it. I did.
But it doesn't matter.
We're going to get punished and demoted.
Sentinel Prime saw the whole thing.
This is so embarrassing.
It's clear.
Orion Pax.
D-16.
What you two did today was
one of the craziest things I've ever seen.
Sir, this is all my idea,
and we're so sorry.
I loved it!
You did?
How could anyone not love it?
You gave my best racers
a real run for their money.
So we're not getting demoted?
Demoted?
Demoted.
Yeah.
What is happening?
The fact of the matter is, we're halfway
into the first shift since the race ended,
and that mining crew
has already reached 150% quota.
You inspired them to work harder!
Sentinel Prime, sir,
we joined the race
to show everyone our potential,
that we bots can do more than just mine--
Outstanding! I love a bot
that can think for himself.
Perhaps you two could tour the mines,
speak to your brethren
and help them see their potential.
Wow!
Okay, great. That sounds incredible.
I would love to--
Sir, it's time.
Yes.
I'm sorry, friends. We're preparing
our next travel to the surface.
But in the meantime,
I've got a treat for you. Hang tight.
Airachnid, have someone escort these
heroes to my personal service facilities.
Best care in Iacon.
Until next time, legends.
Sentinel Prime. The Sentinel Prime!
-You still mad at me?
-I am less mad at you.
I'm telling you, D, I got a feeling that
everything's gonna change,
and we're gonna go--
Miners!
Hi, Darkwing.
-No, no, no!
-No! No!
Wait! You don't understand!
We were supposed to go
to Sentinel Prime's service pod!
You two dolts aren't going to see anyone
ever again. I'll make sure of that.
You're making a mistake! Ask Sentinel!
I hate that guy!
You! How did you get down here?
There's no access to this level.
There is nobody down here but me.
Oh, my gosh, you're real!
You're others! You're... not me!
You're here and you're not me!
-Yeah.
-Awesome!
I am so sorry.
That must have been weird for you.
I just haven't had a lot of company since
they put me down here in sublevel 50.
Fifty? But there are only 40 sublevels.
That's what I thought!
Turns out there are ten more,
and they are not pleasant.
Probably why nobody ever
really talks about them.
-How long have you been down here?
-How long have I been here?
Let's see, somewhere between
a long time and forever.
I mean, I had other jobs,
but I kept getting reassigned
'cause I'm so good at what I do.
I'm B-127, by the way.
But you can call me B.
And I'm actually
working on some nicknames.
The one I'm floating right now
is Badassatron,
which is actually
pronounced "Badassatron."
-But if you have any critiques--
-Yeah, great. How do we get out of here?
Great question. You don't.
-We don't?
-Nope.
We have limited access
to the waste management area,
but the new shift manager there
does not like distractions.
No, they prefer we stay here
on the task at hand.
Which is?
The scrap comes in from the chute there
onto the conveyor belt.
Our job is to look for anything
that might be worth salvaging
before it hits the furnace
and gets smelted.
So you watch garbage burn.
Yes!
It is so great that you're here now.
I can't wait to learn
everything about you.
And then tell you everything about me!
I have a lot of hopes and dreams
that I am just dying to share
with one or two new best friends.
Yeah, I would love to--
Where are my manners?
Come on. I'll introduce you
to the rest of the crew.
Hey, guys, we've got company!
This is EP-508,
this is A-A-Tron,
and this fella here is Steve.
"Steve"?
Yeah, he's foreign.
Question: Do they talk back to you?
They're not real.
-Geez, you think I'm that crazy?
-No, it's just you've been down here a--
No, I was talking to Steve.
Classic Steve.
-What is that?
-Look at this guy.
It's coming from inside.
Steve! No!
-I am so sorry.
-Steve!
-We can fix it, don't worry.
-No! My Steve!
Quintesson ambush!
Calling the High Guard
for immediate support. Immediate support!
That's Alpha Trion.
One of the Primes?
Repeat, Zeta Prime has fallen!
-It's an SOS message.
-Protect the Matrix!
Sending location coordinates.
Holy Primus!
Those are coordinates
to a location on the surface.
This could be where the Primes died
in the Quintesson war.
Which means this is where we could find
the Matrix of Leadership.
What are you talking about? It's an old
beacon inside a statue made of garbage.
Or it's a clue of how we could find
the Matrix of Leadership.
No. No way. Absolutely not!
Come on. This could be our chance
to show everyone we're not--
You already tried to "show everyone"
in the race you tricked me into running
which got us stuck down here
in this waste hole with this...
really cool guy.
Thank you.
I'm just saying--
There's a reason no one goes
to the surface. It's dangerous!
I'm waiting right here
until Sentinel Prime finds us.
Okay. Yeah.
Well, we'll just stay here forever.
That cool with you, B?
Forever? This is great!
I have new coworkers and roommates.
There's plenty of room
now that Steve is dead.
I usually sleep on the conveyor belt,
but you can have it.
I'll sleep in the corner next to A-A-Tron.
Plenty of room for you to stretch out,
too, 'cause you're taller than I am.
You know what I mean?
Hey, D. What do you think
Sentinel's reaction would be
if you personally handed him
the Matrix of Leadership that you found?
Okay, stop.
I know what you're trying to do.
And it's definitely working. I'm in.
Yeah, buddy.
How do we get to the surface?
You kidding me? The surface?
Easy. I know a way.
But it won't be easy.
Why is there so much trash?
Warn me next time, please.
My mouth was open.
Only 49 sublevels to go!
Waste-disposal trains
are the only vehicles
that go all the way to the surface.
Yeah, but they don't allow passengers.
The trains are autonomous.
Yeah, that's the "won't be easy" part.
It's perfect.
We'll be safe inside the train.
That's the last one. Send her up!
Hold up! One more.
I'll lock it down.
Thanks for being an idiot,
whoever you are.
Turning you in will definitely get me
promoted back up a rank or two.
Got her!
No, wait. I--
-Elita! Stop!
-Orion?
Hold on. Let me--
Security! Sound the ala--
-She's headed to the engine!
-Don't worry, I got this.
Hold on. Let me explain!
We're on a mission!
So am I. To ruin your life.
Elita, wait. We found a message.
-We know where--
-Hey, look out.
This bot is crazy! Who is she?
Dead end, Elita. There's no way...
Well, she's gone.
Why? Why am I doing this?
Why am I doing this?
Climb faster!
Gotcha!
The surface.
It's beautiful.
I am speechless.
Elita, listen to me.
We know where the Matrix of Leadership is.
Oh, sure. And I'm really a Prime.
I just prefer loading
crates of toxic waste.
Where did you get this?
From my friend Steve. Orion killed him.
-I did not kill Steve.
-He was never alive.
-What?
-Look.
Sentinel told us
he was going to the surface,
and then we found this message.
We figured that we could hand deliver it
to him or scout the locations ourselves.
Whichever comes first.
This was too important to wait.
It will change all of our lives.
No, no, no.
I'm not going to get demoted again
because of you.
I'm turning this rig around
and I'm notifying--
Hey, guys? Guys?
What is that?
Is it getting bigger?
Or closer?
No, no, no.
Are you closing?
Don't close. Stop closing.
It's closed!
Come on!
Now I know why
no one comes to the surface!
Elita?
You okay?
-Please stop punching me in the face.
-Help me! Help!
Iacon... The train...
-Where's the train?
-Relax, okay? Here it comes.
And there it goes.
Okay, I was wrong about that.
It was going the other way.
Okay, so I think this is us,
and if we follow the path to--
Now you listen to me,
Mr. Zero-Seconds-Since-My-Last-Accident!
I'll go on your little quest
'cause I don't have a choice.
But I carry the map, I navigate,
and if this leads to nothing,
then I'm dragging you and those
two idiot go-bots back to Iacon City
and to the first supervisor depot we see,
at which point you will explain
everything that's happened
using words that reflect me
in a very positive light! Got it?
Yeah, okay. Deal. Great. All right.
-Let's go!
-She's joining us?
Fantastic!
Hi there. Elita, right?
Am I saying that right?
Wanted to formally introduce myself.
I'm B-127. You kneed me
in the face earlier, back there.
You can call me B. Or Badassatron.
It's a nickname some of the guys gave me.
I don't know.
I didn't give it to myself or anything.
Actually, it's pronounced "Badassatron,"
in case you were wondering.
Badassatron.
You like that, right?
-Badass--
-I'm gonna need you to talk less.
Sure! Yeah. No problem.
What am I talking less about, my nickname?
That's fine with me.
Got some mountains over here...
Hey. You're thinking about what you'll say
when you hand the Matrix
to Sentinel, aren't you?
I can't help it.
D, we're really doing this.
So glad I'm out here with you.
This was a great idea.
I'm just having a good time.
How much further is the Matrix on the map?
Make an educated guesstimate.
This is the coolest thing that has ever
happened to anyone anywhere.
I'm telling you!
Not one, not two, not three, but four
Four best friends
Who are walking through the door
-There's no doors, we're outside.
-Hey, look, there's more of it over here.
-What is it?
-It's not metal.
It's like some kind of weird nature.
It's weird.
So are they.
Going to the Matrix with my best friends
What was that?
I think this is not right. We should go.
-Yeah, good idea.
-Run!
What are we running from?
-What is that?
-Oh, no.
-It's a Quintesson ship.
-What?
What do we do? What do we do?
Quiet.
It's scanning for life-forms. Move, move!
Wait!
Go, go, go, go!
Come on! They're not gonna make it.
What were they searching for?
-Someone to hug, B. How should I know?
-I'm not waiting around to find out.
This way. We're close.
Quintessons haven't been here
for 50 cycles.
It doesn't make sense.
There's nothing out here.
A cave with teeth.
Nothing scary about that.
Knives coming out of the ceiling. Amazing.
Everyone, do we have to go insi--
Okay, yep, we're going in.
Why shouldn't we?
Just walking into the scariest place
I've ever seen in my entire life.
This is ridiculous.
I don't believe it.
The Primes.
We're here.
Megatronus Prime.
Zeta Prime.
The Matrix!
It's gone.
Let's keep looking.
Hey, guys!
It's Alpha Trion!
He's powered down.
But his spark is still lit.
Quintesson ambush!
Attack!
Message before--
Whoa, whoa, it's okay! It's okay.
You're safe now.
The war is over.
I failed you, old friend.
You deserved so much better than this end.
No, you didn't fail.
We heard your message.
We've come to find the Matrix.
Your transformation cogs.
What happened to you?
Who are you?
We're cogless miners, from Iacon.
Miners? Why?
Well, we've had to drill for Energon
ever since it stopped flowing.
Impossible.
That's why we came, to fix things.
If we find the Matrix of Leadership
and get it to Sentinel Prime, he can fix--
Sentinel is no Prime.
What?
He's broken. Fantastic.
What are you talking about?
Why would you say that?
Sentinel Prime is our protector.
He's been saving us from the Quintessons--
You have not been saved.
You've been living a lie.
I saw the truth with my own eyes.
Come. I will show you.
For thousands of cycles,
the war with the Quintessons
had been a brutal conflict.
Until Sentinel,
the principal aide to the Primes,
intercepted an enemy transmission.
There was going to be a secret gathering
of Quintesson commanders.
Their elimination could end the war.
It was a mission so important,
we Primes took it on ourselves.
We agreed to meet Sentinel
for his sensitive intel in secret,
here in this cave.
But we were not alone.
-Quintessons!
-They're here!
-It's a trap!
-Battle positions!
-Hold the line!
-Primus be with us!
For Cybertron!
We were outnumbered, but stood as one.
Our victory was near.
Until we were betrayed.
Sentinel, why?
For all the power of Cybertron.
But Sentinel never understood
the true power of what he desired.
The Matrix of Leadership
can only be wielded
by one that Primus himself deems worthy.
And Sentinel most certainly was not.
No!
Wait. Hold on.
You're saying that
the Matrix of Leadership just vanished?
No.
No, no, no. That is impossible.
I don't believe it.
Why would Sentinel do that?
To make a bargain.
A bargain? With who?
With the new rulers of Cybertron.
The Quintessons.
There are so many.
He's here.
Sentinel Prime is here.
-Keep your eyes open.
-They always are.
I load those crates.
Those are filled with contaminated metal.
I don't understand.
What do the Quintessons want
with toxic waste?
Our Energon.
-Traitor!
-D, no.
I know what I promised you,
but our mines, they're running out!
There's barely enough Energon for us.
I swear I will get you the rest.
Triple-time every mining shift.
No miner gets a break
until I get my Energon.
All of it! Let's go.
Now you have seen the truth.
Every day...
Every single day of my life
has been a lie.
My God, I knew it!
Deep down,
I always felt something was off.
He deceived everyone.
Sentinel bought himself power
and then put us to work
paying off his debt.
I can't believe it.
Well, obviously, I can believe it.
I just saw it. But I still...
I can't believe it.
Sentinel lied to my face.
It was all a sham.
How could we have been so gullible?
This is going to change everything.
You just had to do it, didn't you?
Me? What did I do?
You just had to go to the surface,
had to enter the Iacon 5000.
You just had to break protocol!
-Who cares about protocol?
-I do! I care!
Because nothing bad happens
when you stay on protocol!
Sentinel Prime has been forcing us to work
in the mines until our gears strip,
and all the while he's been giving
the Energon away to our greatest enemies!
And what do you think he's gonna do
to us when he finds out that we know?
I'm not thinking about
what he's going to do,
I'm thinking about what we're going to do.
Well, that's the whole thing!
You're never thinking about anything else,
just yourself!
Fantastic! Another Orion Pax master plan.
I can't wait to hear this.
Don't you want to stop him?
No, I want to kill him!
I want to put Sentinel in chains
and march him through the mines
so everyone can see him
for the false Prime that he is!
I want him to suffer
and then to die in darkness.
But we all know that it doesn't matter
what I want, right, Pax?
The fact is,
we're just cogless bots. Right?
We had limited options, and now...
now we have none.
No son or daughter of Cybertron
is born without a cog.
Oh, yeah. I've been with myself
since I came online,
and this slot's always been empty.
So what are you saying? Are you saying--
No. No way.
Nobody could be that evil,
not even Sentinel.
He removed your cogs
before you came online.
We were born
with transformation cogs, but he...
He took them from us.
What defines a Transformer
is not the cog in his chest
but the spark that resides in their core.
A spark that gives you the will
to make your world better.
My fellow Primes had that spark.
And I see their strength in you.
Take their cogs
and access your full potential.
Prima.
Onyx.
Alchemist.
Micronus.
Warriors of noble spirit,
loyalty, strength.
Their uniqueness enhanced by these.
They were one. You are one.
All are one!
Wait. We have... You gave us...
The ability to change your world.
How you choose to use that power
is up to you.
They've found us.
Oh, yes! Time to fight back!
No. You must return to Iacon City
and alert everyone.
Embedded in this are the records
I have shown you.
-Use it to reveal the truth.
-We will.
This tunnel leads to the mountains.
Cybertron's future is in your hands.
We're out of time. We got to move!
Wait. We can't just leave you here.
Your fight will come, my friend.
Primus has a purpose for us all.
But this fight...
This fight is mine.
Now go!
Stand down, old-timer.
Old, you say?
Not too old for you.
We need to hurry!
I still think we have better odds fighting
than outrunning them.
Wait! We have cogs. We can transform now.
-That's right. Everyone ready?
-I was born ready.
On three. One--
How do we use these things?
I don't know. Just try.
It's working. It's working!
My head! My head!
Help! Help!
This is not faster!
Come on!
And transform!
Wheels! I need wheels!
Wow.
-We're alive!
-I've never moved that fast.
-That was incredible!
-See me slide all over the place?
Yes!
Hey, whoa, buddy. You okay?
I'm great. Are you kidding me?
We can transform!
We transform!
Oh, hey! I know.
We're wasting time.
We have to get back to Iacon.
Looks like the fastest way
back to Iacon is--
Here, I got it.
Whoa. What are you doing?
-Don't worry about it. I got it.
-But be careful.
Our proof is inside,
and you're spilling it everywhere.
I... got... it.
Okay.
Follow me.
Alpha Trion!
You are still alive.
Would you look at that?
You look horrible.
Traitor. You are a disgrace.
Primus will surely--
Uh-huh. Yes. Shut up.
I seized an opportunity
to take control of my future.
Anything to get out of working for you
and that boring council of elders.
Seriously, I would watch you Primes
spend half the day losing a war
and the other half sitting around
waxing poetic about loyalty and honor.
And now look at you.
Hear my words: You will fall.
And a new Prime will rise--
There you go again.
I don't want to listen
to any more speeches.
There were others in the cave with you.
Who are they?
They are to be your undoing.
You've lost, Sentinel.
Nothing you can do--
Didn't I just say no speeches?
You heard me, right?
This is what I'm talking about.
Unbelievable.
All of them are like that.
So disrespectful.
Okay. Hunt down the others.
With pleasure.
Hey, buddy.
Hey.
You've been a little quiet.
Are you all right?
All I can think about
is Sentinel's smirking face.
He must pay for what he's done.
Someone has to do something.
We are.
With Alpha's proof inside that device,
we will show everyone the truth.
You honestly believe it'll be that easy?
Iacon doesn't want to hear the truth.
They worship Sentinel.
There's got to be a better way
to bring him down.
We have to trust that
everyone will believe what we show them.
I trusted Sentinel!
With everything.
I will never trust
a so-called leader ever again.
There's only one bot I know I can--
All right. Wake them up.
Now, are you spies
or just incompetent lackeys?
-We're not spies.
-But he is incompetent.
Scanning electrical impulses.
He speaks the truth.
That just means he believes himself,
like any spy would.
Why is he gagged?
He wouldn't stop talking.
Even when he was unconscious?
Especially when he was unconscious!
Enough!
Two options for you!
One, we slowly dismantle each of you
one bolt and screw at a time
and really make sure you feel it.
Or two:
In exchange for a quick death,
you give us intel on the Energon trains,
access to the mines
or anything else
that could hurt your boss, Sentinel Prime.
Who exactly are you guys?
The Cybertronian High Guard!
I told you it wasn't tight enough!
-Prestigious defenders of Iacon.
-Prestigious?
He's right. I read all about you
in the archives.
You were the most legendary warriors
in all of Cybertron.
Look, look, look!
That's Starscream,
and you're Shockwave, and Soundwave.
Gosh, raise your hand if "wave" is
in your name. There's a lot of "waves."
Silence!
The yellow annoying one is correct.
We were once the High Guard.
We witnessed Sentinel's betrayal,
saw the Primes fall.
Since that day,
we've been fighting from the shadows,
doing whatever we can
to sabotage Sentinel.
Well, that's great! We're--
Okay, okay. We're good. Everyone relax.
I'm just saying we're allies.
We were on our way back to Iacon,
and now with your help, we can unify
Cybertron against Sentinel Prime.
The idea of a unified Cybertron is a myth.
All that counts
is the strength of one bot over another!
Okay. So these guys are a little intense.
Yeah, just a little.
Hey! What are you doing?
I tell you what I'm not doing.
I'm not cowering in some busted ship,
playing king of the throne.
I'm not pretending
like I'm making a difference
by throwing one punch
and then running away to hide!
I found out that Sentinel is rotten today
and I'm gonna make him pay for it today!
You think you can insult me
and just walk away?
No one leaves here unless I say so.
Is that right?
Well, how can you say so
with my head in your teeth?
D!
Hit me! Do it!
Come on! Yeah, more!
D-16! D-16! D-16!
You want to see the strength
of one bot over another, huh?
Is that all you've got, tough bot?
Let's go! Do it! Come on!
Please! I beg you!
Stop! D, he's not the enemy!
Bear witness!
This is the last time I show mercy!
Decide right now:
You can stay here in hiding,
bowing before your pathetic leader,
or follow me as we march on Iacon
and I take down Sentinel once and for all!
D-16! D-16! D-16!
B, come on!
Engage all hostiles! I've got the bridge!
Elita, get down!
I feel like someone dropped a cliff on me.
Where are the others?
Sentinels troops took as many prisoners
as they could carry.
They got D-16 and B.
Oh, no.
And half of those High-Guard nutjobs.
Our proof.
It's gone.
So, what do we do now?
D was right.
-About what?
-Everything.
Look at it. Look around.
This is a disaster.
It's all my fault.
I should have stayed on protocol.
Listen to me.
I really want you to hear this.
Are you listening?
I'm better than you.
Yeah, okay, I'm hearing you.
I'm better than you in every way,
except you have hope.
You always have. You went back
into the mine to rescue Jazz.
You snuck up to the surface
to find the Matrix of Leadership.
Yeah, and how'd that work out?
My point is that your instincts tell you
to break protocol for a reason.
This blind optimism that you have
is why you make
such bold and courageous choices
that are also extremely stupid.
First time giving a pep talk?
You're inspiring.
You can envision a better future
that no one else can see.
And if we ever want to see
B and D-16 again,
that is the Orion Pax
that we need right now.
Listen to me.
We can do this.
Those Energon trains
will be heading back to Iacon.
If we intercepted one--
Hell yes, I can reroute it.
What else do we need?
Well, my bold instincts tell me
we have to recruit some nutjobs.
I was afraid you'd say that.
Shockwave, Soundwave. You in the back.
In order to save our captured friends,
we have to act now.
How about I blast you back to Iacon?
She punched me in my eye!
Everyone, shut up!
All of you. Listen to him.
Most likely, our friends are being held
captive at the top of Sentinel's tower.
A surprise attack would give us
a chance to rescue them.
Impossible. We do not have
enough soldiers or a way inside.
Elita will get us in.
And I will get more troops.
Why should we follow you?
We will follow you.
Attention, High Guard. Prepare for battle.
What is our first move?
We roll out.
What?
Louder.
Transform and roll out!
I don't understand.
Why are we still alive?
Look at this rowdy bunch! The High Guard!
You know, you guys have been
tough to find.
Every trip to the surface,
I've been searching for you.
Tracking the bots in the cave
led me right to them.
-You captured Starscream!
-It was too easy.
I'm going to rip you apart piece by piece
so that your death is painful!
-You'll regret the day you were--
-You sound ridiculous. It's weird.
D-16, what a tragic story you'll be.
Atop the leaderboard in your sector
and secretly a traitor.
I'm not a traitor. You're the traitor.
Nuh-uh. You, all of you, are traitors.
You've been working with the Quintessons
to sabotage my expeditions.
You're the reason why I haven't found
the Matrix of Leadership yet.
None of that is true!
Trust me, it'll be very true
when I'm executing you
in front of all of Iacon.
Because down here,
the truth is what I make it.
Well, well. What's this about?
I'm not kneeling in front of you.
Feeling confident, are we?
You don't scare me. You want to know why?
Please.
Because I don't have
anything left to lose.
You took it all.
I sure did.
Megatronus Prime.
Of course you were a fan.
Megatronus was the coolest Prime!
The biggest! The baddest! The toughest!
That's why, after I killed him,
I took his cog for myself.
He was greater than you'll ever be!
I don't know. I'm pretty great.
But I can understand
why you'd want to wear his face over mine.
Here.
Let's make sure it doesn't come off.
Okay.
I can do this.
You can't be serious.
We just worked 22 shifts without a break!
These miners need rest
and time to repair--
Sentinel Prime wants more Energon.
So get back in the mines
before I make you get back in--
-Who was that?
-Did you see who that was?
That can't be him.
Is that...
It can't be.
-Orion?
-Jazz.
Is it really you?
Yeah, I know I look a little different.
"Little"?
There's nothing "little" about you.
How is this possible?
Sentinel told us
you died from your race injuries.
Sentinel is a liar.
What?
I know how this will sound coming from me.
I was never the most focused miner.
But as you can see,
everything is different now.
I went to the surface
and I learned the truth.
My friends,
we were all born with transformation cogs.
And then Sentinel, he stole them from us.
He took away
our ability to make our own decisions.
He stole our freedom.
But now I'm offering you
your first real choice.
You can work a 23rd shift
and mine yourself to death
or fight back against Sentinel with me.
Right now.
-How are we supposed to do that?
-We can't fight. We don't have cogs.
What defines a Transformer
is not the cog in its chest
but the spark that resides in their core.
A spark that gives you the will
to make your world better.
And that spark,
Sentinel can never take from us.
There's not enough of us.
We'd need an army.
And we have one. Elita is bringing troops.
We are not alone in this.
If we want to be
in control of our own destiny,
we will have to fight for it.
Now is the time
for us to stand up for ourselves.
Stand up for this injustice.
I promise you this fight will be worth it.
Follow me.
Nothing can stop us
when we stand together.
Together as one.
Orion Pax! Orion Pax! Orion Pax!
Elita, it's time.
You got it.
Buckle up, Blinky. We're going in.
Not a good idea.
D, stay down.
Well, that's a shame.
You really were a great miner.
We've got a breach! Protect Sentinel!
Looks like they spotted us.
It's about to get bumpy.
High Guard, eject.
Come on! Move out!
There's too many. We have to abort!
We're not gonna make it.
Metal to the pedal, miners!
Let's break some protocol!
That's what I'm talking about, Pax!
That's intense.
You can't win, miner. I see everything!
That's right, you do.
Except the tower
we're about to crash into.
What's going on?
Hey.
What has he done to you?
This is nothing compared to
what I'm gonna do to Sentinel.
Soundwave, free the prisoners.
I know how to stop him.
Airachnid is the answer.
-I'm doing this my way.
-D!
Yes!
I got a battle mask!
Elita! Battle mask!
It appeared when this guy tried to--
Sword hands? I have sword hands!
What the--
Badassatron.
Where's Sentinel?
You pathetic little twits.
Did you really think that you could
knock down everything I've built?
It's over, Sentinel.
You can't escape the truth.
What truth? That I plucked the cogs
from your newborn chests?
Forced you to mine so that I could pay off
the Quintessons and live like a king?
None of that matters!
Because the truth is what I make it.
Incoming!
-He's too strong.
-I have a plan.
-We need Airachnid.
-Airachnid?
-We need her memory.
-Where is she?
Found her!
Elita!
Do not break her.
Bring her to the broadcast station.
We'll meet you there.
Easier said than done.
-I said, don't break her!
-Relax! I'm being very gentle.
Orion! Orion, look! I have sword hands!
I can see that.
I'm gonna cut these guys. Watch.
Come here!
You can jab them later. We got to go.
Yeah!
Excuse me. You can't be in--
B!
-These are not the bad guys.
-Why did you cut the door?
What? No, I didn't... That was...
It was already like that. Right?
-Yes, that's right.
-That's right, yes. It was already like...
Attention, Iacon City.
Stand by for a live transmission
from Sentinel Prime.
What's wrong, D-16?
Rise up!
That's why, after I killed him--
That's why, after I killed him,
I took his cog for myself.
...cog for myself.
What truth? That I plucked the cogs
from your newborn chests?
Forced you to mine so that I could pay off
the Quintessons and live like a king?
What truth? That I plucked the cogs
from your newborn chests?
Forced you to mine so that I could pay off
the Quintessons and live like a king?
I'm working my miners as hard as I can.
I swear I will get you the rest!
Liar!
We trusted you!
Traitor!
Pax, we did it.
D!
D-16.
We can lead Cybertron together!
Don't do this!
What are you doing?
It's over, D.
Everyone in Iacon knows the truth.
So do I!
He took everything from us!
I have to do this!
No, you don't.
Rebuilding Iacon cannot begin
with an execution.
He deserves to die! Can't you see that?
We're better than this.
Don't be like Sentinel.
Pax,
you need to move out of my way
before I move you myself.
D, listen--
Stop!
No!
No, no, no, no. Why?
Why did you do that? Why?
D, no.
I'm done saving you.
The Age of Primes has ended!
No more false prophets!
Follow me and you will never again
be deceived.
Rise up!
Rise up! Rise up!
Orion Pax,
your noble sacrifice for the greater good
has proven you worthy
in the eyes of Primus.
He entrusts in you
the future of Cybertron
and the Matrix of Leadership!
I will lead us all into the future!
I...
am...
Megatron!
Arise...
Optimus Prime.
Burn it down!
All of it!
All hail Megatron!
-He's gonna kill everyone.
-We have to stop him. Come on.
Stop! It's over.
It's over when every last one
of his followers is dead!
Impossible.
Primus gave you the Matrix.
We could've built the future together.
I'll build it myself
after I tear down everyone in my way!
We were given
the power to change our world,
and you chose to destroy it.
Just like Sentinel.
You have betrayed Cybertron
and its citizens.
And you betrayed me.
Go.
Take the High Guard and leave.
You are banished from Iacon.
It didn't have to end this way.
This isn't over, Prime.
High Guard, follow me!
The line between friend and enemy
is not as clear as I once believed.
Once it's crossed, there's no going back.
Because some transformations
are permanent.
Hey, Megatronus Prime. Nice.
Oh, yeah. Well, he's my hero.
-The greatest Prime to ever live.
-I'm D-16.
-Orion Pax.
-You ever mine Energon before?
-No.
-You?
-No. I hear it's dangerous.
Well, I'll tell you what.
You watch my back,
I'll promise to watch yours.
All right.
Thanks, Pax.
A new beginning for Cybertron.
And a new leader.
Yes, about that.
I could use some help from a bot
who is better than me in every way.
Who, me? Oh, no.
I have a pretty sweet gig
working in waste management.
Well, Captain, I do owe you a promotion.
How's Major Elita sound?
How about Commander?
Even better.
And I'm sorry, B, but I cannot let you
go back to sublevel 50.
I may be a Prime now,
but I'm gonna need you by my side.
Are you serious?
This is the greatest day of my life.
I get to work for the government.
Okay. So that's new.
I'm sorry. What is happening?
And now we stand here together as one...
proving we all have
the power to transform,
to become who we were destined to be,
to right wrongs, to make our world better.
Because here, freedom and autonomy
are the rights of all sentient beings.
Here, all are truly Autobots.
This message is a warning
to all Quintessons.
If you dare return to Cybertron,
the Autobots will be waiting.
I will be waiting.
I am Optimus Prime.
Hey, guys! Great news, the Energon's back!
And I have a cog and I can transform!
It's a long story. I'll fill you in later.
And here's the best part.
My hands are straight-up swords.
Watch this. Sword hands!
No!
Sentinel the betrayer is dead.
But his death has given life
to a new enemy.
A stronger enemy.
A personal enemy.
We will not be blinded by his deception.
We are the ones who are...
Decepticons!
Rise up!
Rise up! Rise up!